Letter X

Dear Mother,

You and my good Father may wonder that you have not had a Letter from me in so many Weeks; but a sad, sad Scene has been the Occasion of it. For, to be sure, now it is too plain, that all your Cautions were well-grounded. O my dear Mother! I am miserable, truly miserable!—But yet, don’t be frighted, I am honest!—God, of his Goodness, keep me so!

O this Angel of a Master! this fine Gentleman! this gracious Benefactor to your poor Pamela! who was to take care of me at the Prayer of his good dying Mother; who was so careful of me, lest I should be drawn in by Lord Davers’s Nephew; that he would not let me go to Lady Davers’s: This very Gentleman (yes, I must call him Gentleman, tho’ he has fallen from the Merit of that Title) has degraded himself to offer Freedoms to his poor Servant! He has now shew’d himself in his true Colours, and to me, nothing appears so black and so frightful.

I have not been idle; but have writ from time to time how he, by sly mean Degrees, exposed his wicked Views: But somebody stole my Letter, and I know not what is become of it. It was a very long one. I fear he that was mean enough to do bad things, in one respect, did not stick at this; but be it as it will, all the Use he can make of it will be, that he may be asham’d of his Part; I not of mine. For he will see I was resolv’d to be honest, and glory’d in the Honesty of my poor Parents. I will tell you all, the next Opportunity; for I am watch’d, and such-like, very narrowly; and he says to Mrs. Jervis, This Girl is always scribbling; I think she may be better employ’d. And yet I work all Hours with my Needle, upon his Linen, and the fine Linen of the Family; and am besides about flowering him a Waistcoat.—But, Oh! my Heart’s broke almost; for what am I likely to have for my Reward, but Shame and Disgrace, or else ill Words, and hard Treatment! I’ll tell you all soon, and hope I shall find my long Letter.

Your most afflicted Daughter.

I must he and him him now; for he has lost his Dignity with me!

Letter XI

Dear Mother,

Well, I can’t find my Letter, and so I’ll tell you all, as briefly as I can. All went well enough in the main for some time after my last Letter but one. At last, I saw some Reason to suspect; for he would look upon me, whenever he saw me, in such a manner, as shew’d not well; and at last he came to me, as I was in the Summer-house in the little Garden, at work with my Needle, and Mrs. Jervis was just gone from me; and I would have gone out; but he said, No, don’t go, Pamela; I have something to say to you; and you always fly me so, whenever I come near you, as if you was afraid of me.

I was all confounded; and said at last; It does not become your poor Servant to stay in your Presence, Sir, without your Business requir’d it; and I hope I shall always know my Place.

Well, says he, my Business does require it sometimes, and I have a mind you should stay to hear what I have to say to you.

I stood all confounded, and began to tremble, and the more when he took me by the Hand; for now no Soul was near us.

My Sister Davers, said he, (and seem’d, I thought, to be as much at a Loss for Words as I) would have had you live with her; but she would not do for you what I am resolv’d to do, if you continue faithful and obliging. What say’st thou, my Girl, said he, with some Eagerness, hadst thou not rather stay with me than go to my Sister Davers? He look’d so, as fill’d me with Affrightment; I don’t know how; wildly I thought.

I said, when I could speak, Your Honour will forgive your poor Servant; but as you have no Lady for me to wait upon, and my good Lady has been now dead this Twelve-month, I had rather, if it would not displease you, wait upon Lady Davers, because——

I was proceeding; and he said a little hastily—Because you’re a little Fool, and know not what’s good for yourself. I tell you, I will make a Gentlewoman of you, if you be obliging, and don’t stand in your own Light; and so saying, he put his Arm about me, and kiss’d me!

Now you will say, all his Wickedness appear’d plainly. I struggled, and trembled, and was so benumb’d with Terror, that I sunk down, not in a Fit, and yet not myself; and I found myself in his Arms, quite void of Strength, and he kissed me two or three times, as if he would have eaten me.—At last I burst from him, and was getting out of the Summer-house; but he held me back, and shut the Door.

I would have given my Life for a Farthing. And he said, I’ll do you no Harm, Pamela; don’t be afraid of me. I said, I won’t stay! You won’t, Hussy, said he! Do you know who you speak to! I lost all Fear, and all Respect, and said, Yes, I do, Sir, too well!—Well may I forget that I am your Servant, when you forget what belongs to a Master.

I sobb’d and cry’d most sadly. What a foolish Hussy you are, said he, have I done you any Harm?—Yes, Sir, said I, the greatest Harm in the World: You have taught me to forget myself, and what belongs to me, and have lessen’d the Distance that Fortune has made between us, by demeaning yourself, to be so free to a poor Servant. Yet, Sir, said I, I will be so bold to say, I am honest, tho’ poor; And if you was a Prince, I would not be otherwise.

He was angry, and said, Who would have you otherwise, you foolish Slut! Cease your blubbering! I own I have demean’d myself; but it was only to try you: If you can keep this Matter secret, you’ll give me the better Opinion of your Prudence; and here’s something, said he, putting some Gold in my Hand, to make you Amends for the Fright I put you to. Go, take a Walk in the Garden, and don’t go in till your blubbering is over: And I charge you say nothing of what has past, and all shall be well, and I’ll forgive you.

I won’t take the Money, indeed, Sir, said I; poor as I am! I won’t take it: for to say Truth, I thought it look’d like taking Earnest; and so I put it upon the Bench; and as he seem’d vex’d and confus’d at what he had done, I took the Opportunity to open the Door, and went out of the Summer-house.

He called to me, and said, Be secret, I charge you, Pamela; and don’t go in yet, as I told you.

O how poor and mean must these Actions be, and how little must they make the best of Gentlemen look, when they offer such things as are unworthy of themselves, and put it into the Power of their Inferiors to be greater than they!

I took a Turn or two in the Garden, but in Sight of the House for fear of the worst, and breathed upon my Hand to dry my Eyes, because I would not be too disobedient. My next shall tell you more.

Pray for me, my dear Father and Mother; and don’t be angry I have not yet run away from this House, so late my Comfort and Delight, but now my Anguish and Terror. I am forc’d to break off, hastily,

Your dutiful and honest Daughter

Letter XII

Dear Mother,

Well, I will now proceed with my sad Story. And so after I had dry’d my Eyes, I went in, and begun to ruminate with myself what I had best to do. Sometimes I thought I would leave the House, and go to the next Town, and wait an Opportunity to get to you; but then I was at a Loss to resolve whether to take away the Things he had given me or no, and how to take them away: Sometimes I thought to leave them behind me, and only go with the Cloaths on my Back; but then I had two Miles and a half, and a By-way, to go to the Town; and being pretty well dress’d, I might come to some harm, almost as bad as what I would run away from; and then may-be, thought I, it will be reported, I have stolen something, and so was forc’d to run away; and to carry a bad Name back with me to my dear poor Parents, would be a sad thing indeed!—O how I wish’d for my grey Russet again, and my poor honest Dress, with which you fitted me out, and hard enough too you had to do it, God knows, for going to this Place, when I was but twelve Years old, in my good Lady’s Days! Sometimes I thought of telling Mrs. Jervis, and taking her Advice, and only feared his Command, to be secret; for, thought I, he may be ashamed of his Actions, and never attempt the like again: And as poor Mrs. Jervis depended upon him, thro’ Misfortunes that had attended her, I thought it would be a sad thing to bring his Displeasure upon her for my sake.

In this Quandary, now considering, now crying, and not knowing what to do, I pass’d the Time in my Chamber till Evening; when desiring to be excused going to Supper, Mrs. Jervis came up to me; and said, Why must I sup without you, Pamela? Come, I see you are troubled at something; tell me what is the Matter.

I begg’d I might be permitted to lie with her on Nights; for I was afraid of Spirits, and they would not hurt such a good Person as she. That was a silly Excuse, she said; for why was you not afraid of Spirits before? Indeed I did not think of that. But you shall be my Bedfellow with all my Heart, said she, let your Reason be what it will; only come down to Supper. I begg’d to be excus’d; for, said I, I have been crying so, that it will be taken Notice of by my Fellow-servants; and I will hide nothing from you, Mrs. Jervis, when we are a-bed.

She was so good to indulge me, and went down to Supper; but made more haste to come up to-bed; and told the Servants, that I should lie with her, because she said she could not rest well, and she would get me to read her to sleep, because she knew I lov’d reading, as she said.

When we were alone, I told her every bit and crumb of the Matter; for I thought, tho’ he had bid me not, yet if he should come to know I had told, it would be no worse; for to keep a Secret of such a Nature, I thought would be to deprive myself of the good Advice which I never wanted more; and might encourage him to think I did not resent it as I ought, and would keep worse Secrets, and so make him do worse by me. Was I right, my dear Mother?

Mrs. Jervis could not help mingling Tears with my Tears; for I cry’d all the Time I told her the Story; and begg’d her to advise me what to do; and I shew’d her my dear Father’s two Letters, and she praised the Honesty and Inditing of them; and said pleasing things to me of you both. But she begg’d I would not think of leaving my Service; for, says she, in all Likelihood, you behav’d so virtuously, that he will be asham’d of what he has done, and never offer the like to you again: Tho’, my dear Pamela, said she, I fear more for your Prettiness than for any thing else; because the best Man in the Land might love you; so she was pleased to say. She said she wished it was in her Power to live independent; that then she would take a little private House, and I should live with her like her Daughter.

And so, as you order’d me to take her Advice, I resolved to tarry to see how things went, without he was to turn me away; altho’, in your first Letter, you order’d me to come away the Moment I had any Reason to be apprehensive. So, dear Father and Mother, it is not Disobedience, I hope, that I stay; for I could not expect a Blessing, or the good Fruits of your Prayers for me, if I was disobedient.

All the next Day I was very sad, and began to write my long Letter. He saw me writing, and said (as I mention’d) to Mrs. Jervis, That Girl is always scribbling; methinks she might find something else to do, or to that purpose. And when I had finish’d my Letter, I put it under the Toilet, in my late Lady’s Dressing-room, where nobody comes but myself and Mrs. Jervis, besides my Master; but when I came up again to seal it up, to my great Concern it was gone; and Mrs. Jervis knew nothing of it; and nobody knew of my Master’s having been near the Place in the time; so I have been sadly troubled about it: But Mrs. Jervis, as well as I, thinks he has it some how or other; and he appears cross and angry, and seems to shun me, as much as he said I did him. It had better be so than worse!

But he has order’d Mrs. Jervis to bid me not spend so much time in writing; which is a poor Matter for such a Gentleman as he to take notice of, as I am not idle otherways, if he did not resent what he thought I wrote upon. And this has no very good Look.

But I am a good deal easier since I lie with Mrs. Jervis; tho’ after all, the Fears I live in on one side, and his Frowning and Displeasure at what I do on the other, makes me more miserable than enough.

O that I had never left my Rags nor my Poverty, to be thus expos’d to Temptations on one hand, or Disgusts on the other! How happy was I a-while ago! How miserable now!—Pity and pray for

Your afflicted Pamela.

Letter XIII

My dearest Child,

Our Hearts bleed for your Distress and the Temptations you are tried with. You have our hourly Prayers; and we would have you flee this evil Great House and Man, if you find he renews his Attempts. You ought to have done it at first, had you not had Mrs. Jervis to advise with. We can find no Fault in your Conduct hitherto: But it makes our Hearts ake for fear of the worst. O my Child! Temptations are sore things; but yet without them, we know not our selves, nor what we are able to do.

Your Temptations are very great; for you have Riches, Youth, and a fine Gentleman, as the World reckons him, to withstand; but how great will be your Honour to withstand them! And when we consider your past Conduct, and your virtuous Education, and that you have been bred to be more asham’d of Dishonesty than Poverty, we trust in God that he will enable you to overcome. Yet, as we can’t see but your Life must be a Burden to you, through the great Apprehensions always upon you; and that it may be presumptuous to trust too much to your own Strength; and that you are but very young; and the Devil may put it into his Head to use some Stratagem, of which great Men are full, to decoy you; I think you had best come home to share our Poverty with Safety, than to live with so much Discontent in a Plenty, that itself may be dangerous. God direct you for the best. While you have Mrs. Jervis for an Adviser, and Bedfellow, (and, O my dear Child, that was prudently done of you) we are easier than we should be; and so committing you to God’s blessed Protection, remain

Your truly loving.
but careful, Father and Mother.

Letter XIV

Dear Father and Mother,

Mrs. Jervis and I have liv’d very comfortably together for this Fortnight past; for my Master was all that time at his Lincolnshire Estate, and at his Sister’s the Lady Davers. But he came home Yesterday. He had some Talk with Mrs. Jervis soon after he came home; and mostly about me. He said to her, it seems, Well, Mrs. Jervis, I know Pamela has your good Word; but do you think her of any Use in the Family? She told me, she was surpris’d at the Question; but said, That I was one of the most virtuous and industrious young Creatures that ever she knew. Why that Word virtuous, said he, I pray you? Was there any Reason to suppose her otherwise? Or has any body taken it into their Heads to try her?—I wonder, Sir, says she, you ask me such a Question! Who dare offer any thing to her in such an orderly and well-govern’d House as yours, and under a Master of so good a Character for Virtue and Honour? Your Servant, Mrs. Jervis, says he, for your good Opinion; but pray, if any body did, do you think Pamela would let you know it? Why, Sir, said she; she is a poor innocent young Thing, and I believe has so much Confidence in me, that she would take my Advice as soon as she would her Mother’s. Innocent! again; and virtuous, I warrant! Well, Mrs. Jervis, you abound with your Epithets; but ’tis my Opinion, she is an artful young Baggage; and had I a young handsome Butler or Steward, she’d soon make her Market of one of them, if she thought it worth while to snap at him for a Husband. Alack-a-day, Sir, said she, ’tis early Days with Pamela, and she does not yet think of a Husband, I dare say: And your Steward and Butler are both Men in Years, and think nothing of the Matter. No, said he, if they were younger, they’d have more Wit than to think of such a Girl. I’ll tell you my Mind of her, Mrs. Jervis, I don’t think this same Favourite of yours so very artless a Girl, as you imagine. I am not to dispute with your Honour about her, said Mrs. Jervis; but I dare say, if the Men will let her alone, she’ll never trouble herself about them. Why, Mrs. Jervis, said he, are there any Men that will not let her alone that you know of? No, indeed, Sir, said she; she keeps herself so much to herself, and yet behaves so prudently, that they all esteem her, and shew her as great Respect as if she was a Gentlewoman born.

Ay, says he, that’s her Art, that I was speaking of: But let me tell you, the Girl has Vanity and Conceit, and Pride too, or I am mistaken; and I could give you perhaps an Instance of it. Sir, said she, you can see further than such a poor silly Woman as me; but I never saw any thing but Innocence in her.—And Virtue too, I’ll warrant ye, said he. But suppose I could give you an Instance, where she has talk’d a little too freely of the Kindnesses that have been shew’d her from a certain Quarter; and has had the Vanity to impute a few kind Words utter’d in mere Compassion to her Youth and Circumstances, into a Design upon her, and even dar’d to make free with Names that she ought never to mention but with Reverence and Gratitude; what would you say to that?—Say, Sir! said she, I cannot tell what to say. But I hope Pamela incapable of such Ingratitude.

Well, no more of this silly Girl, says he; you may only advise her, as you are her Friend, not to give herself too much Licence upon the Favours she meets with; and if she stays here, that she will not write the Affairs of my Family purely for an Exercise to her Pen and her Invention. I tell you, she is a subtle artful Gypsey, and time will shew it you.

Was ever the like heard, my dear Father and Mother? It is plain he did not expect to meet with such a Repulse, and mistrusts that I have told Mrs. Jervis, and has my long Letter too that I intended for you; and so is vex’d to the Heart. But, however, I can’t help it. So I had better be thought artful and subtle, than be so, in his Sense; and as light as he makes of the Words Virtue and Innocence in me, he would have made a less angry Construction, had I less deserved that he should do so; for then, may be, my Crime would have been my Virtue with him; naughty Gentleman as he is!—I will soon write again; but must now end with saying, That I am, and shall always be,

Your honest Daughter.

Letter XV

Dear Mother,

I Broke off abruptly my last Letter; for I fear’d he was coming; and so it happen’d. I thrust the Letter into my Bosom, and took up my Work, which lay by me; but I had so little of the Artful, as he called it, that I look’d as confused, as if I had been doing some great Harm.

Sit still, Pamela, said he, and mind your Work, for all me.—You don’t tell me I am welcome home after my Journey to Lincolnshire. It would be hard, Sir, said I, if you was not always welcome to your Honour’s own House.

I would have gone; but he said, Don’t run away, I tell you. I have a Word or two to say to you. Good Sirs, how my Heart went pit-a-pat! When I was a little kind, said he, to you in the Summer-house, and you carry’d yourself so foolishly upon it, as if I had intended to do you great harm, did I not tell you, you should take no Notice of what pass’d, to any Creature? And yet you have made a common Talk of the Matter, not considering either my Reputation or your own.—I made a common Talk of it, Sir, said I! I have nobody to talk to, hardly!

He interrupted me, and said, Hardly! you little Equivocator! what do you mean by hardly? Let me ask you, Have you not told Mrs. Jervis for one? Pray your Honour, said I, all in Agitation, let me go down; for ’tis not for me to hold an Argument with your Honour. Equivocator, again! said he, and took my Hand, what do you talk of an Argument? Is it holding an Argument with me, to answer a plain Question? Answer me what I asked. O good, Sir, said I, let me beg you will not urge me further, for fear I forget myself again, and be sawcy.

Answer me then, I bid you, says he, Have you told Mrs. Jervis? It will be sawcy in you, if you don’t answer me directly to what I ask. Sir, said I, and fain would have pulled my Hand away, may be I should be for answering you by another Question, and that would not become me. What is it, says he, you would say? Speak out!

Then, Sir, said I, why should your Honour be so angry I should tell Mrs. Jervis, or any body else, what passed, if you intended no harm?

Well said, pretty Innocent and Artless! as Mrs. Jervis calls you, said he; and is it thus you taunt and retort upon me, insolent as you are! But still I will be answered directly to my Question? Why then, Sir, said I, I will not tell a Lye for the World: I did tell Mrs. Jervis; for my Heart was almost broke; but I open’d not my Mouth to any other. Very well, Boldface, said he, and Equivocator, again! You did not open your Mouth to any other; but did you not write to some other? Why now, and please your Honour, said I, (for I was quite courageous just then) you could not have asked me this Question, if you had not taken from me my Letter to my Father and Mother, in which, I own, I had broke my Mind freely to them, and asked their Advice, and poured forth my Griefs!

And so I am to be exposed, am I, said he, in my House, and out of my House, to the whole World, by such a Sawcebox as you? No, good Sir, said I, and I hope your Honour won’t be angry with me; it is not me that expose you if I say nothing but the Truth. So, taunting again! Assurance as you are, said he! I will not be thus talk’d to.

Pray, Sir, said I, who can a poor Girl take Advice of, if it must not be of her Father and Mother, and such a good Woman as Mrs. Jervis, who for her Sex-sake, should give it me when asked? Insolence! said he, and stamp’d with his Foot, Am I to be question’d thus by such a one as you? I fell down on my Knees, and said, For God’s sake, your Honour, pity a poor distressed Creature, that knows nothing of her Duty, but how to cherish her Virtue and good Name! I have nothing else to trust to; and tho’ poor and friendless here, yet I have always been taught to value Honesty above my Life. Here’s ado with your Honesty, said he, foolish Girl! Is it not one Part of Honesty, to be dutiful and grateful to your Master, do you think? Indeed, Sir, said I, it is impossible I should be ingrateful to your Honour, or disobedient, or deserve the Names of Boldface and Insolent, which you call me, but when your Commands are contrary to that first Duty, which shall ever be the Principle of my Life!

He seem’d to be moved, and rose up, and walked into the great Chamber two or three Turns, leaving me on my Knees; and I threw my Apron over my Face, and laid my Head on a Chair, and cry’d as if my Heart would break, having no Power to stir.

At last he came in again, but, alas! with Mischief in his Heart! and raising me up, he said, Rise, Pamela, rise; you are your own Enemy. Your perverse Folly will be your Ruin! I tell you this, that I am very much displeased with the Freedoms you have taken with my Name to my House-keeper, as also to your Father and Mother; and you may as well have real Cause to take these Freedoms with me, as to make my Name suffer for imaginary ones: And saying so, he offer’d to take me on his Knee, with some Force. O how I was terrify’d! I said, like as I had read in a Book a Night or two before, Angels, and Saints, and all the Host of Heaven, defend me1! And may I never survive one Moment, that fatal one in which I shall forfeit my Innocence. Pretty Fool! said he, how will you forfeit your Innocence, if you are oblig’d to yield to a Force you cannot withstand? Be easy, said he; for let the worst happen that can, you’ll have the Merit, and I the Blame; and it will be a good Subject for Letters to your Father and Mother, and a Tale into the Bargain for Mrs. Jervis.

He by Force kissed my Neck and Lips; and said, Who ever blamed Lucretia2 but the Ravisher only? and I am content to take all the Blame upon me; as I have already borne too great a Share for what I have deserv’d. May I, said I, Lucretia like, justify myself with my Death, if I am used barbarously? O my good Girl! said he, tauntingly, you are well read, I see; and we shall make out between us, before we have done, a pretty Story in Romance, I warrant ye!

He then put his Hand in my Bosom, and the Indignation gave me double Strength, and I got loose from him, by a sudden Spring, and ran out of the Room; and the next Chamber being open, I made shift to get into it, and threw-to the Door, and the Key being on the Inside, it locked; but he follow’d me so close, he got hold of my Gown, and tore a Piece off, which hung without the Door.

I just remember I got into the Room; for I knew nothing further of the Matter till afterwards; for I fell into a Fit with my Fright and Terror, and there I lay, till he, as I suppose, looking through the Keyhole, spy’d me lying all along upon the Floor, stretch’d out at my Length; and then he call’d Mrs. Jervis to me, who, by his Assistance, bursting open the Door, he went away, seeing me coming to myself; and bid her say nothing of the Matter, if she was wise.

Poor Mrs. Jervis thought it was worse, and cry’d over me like as if she was my Mother; and I was two Hours before I came to myself; and just as I got a little up on my Feet, he coming in, I went away again with the Terror; and so he withdrew again: But he staid in the next Room to let nobody come near us, that his foul Proceedings might not be known.

Mrs. Jervis gave me her Smelling-bottle, and had cut my Laces, and sat me in a great Chair, and he call’d her to him: How is the Girl, said he? I never saw such a Fool in my Life. I did nothing at all to her. Mrs. Jervis could not speak for crying. So, he said, she has told you, it seems, that I was kind to her in the Summer-house, tho’ I’ll assure you, I was quite innocent then as well as now; and I desire you to keep this Matter to yourself, and let me not be nam’d in it.

O Sir, said she, for your Honour’s sake, and for Christ’s sake—But he would not hear her, and said—For your own sake, I tell you, Mrs. Jervis, say not a Word more. I have done her no harm. And I won’t have her stay in my House; prating, perverse Fool, as she is! But since she is so apt to fall into Fits, or at least pretend to do so, prepare her to see me To-morrow after Dinner, in my Mother’s Closet, and do you be with her, and you shall hear what passes between us.

And so he went out in a Pet, and order’d his Chariot and Four to be got ready, and went away a Visiting somewhere.

Mrs. Jervis then came to me, and I told her all that had happen’d, and said I was resolv’d not to stay in the House; and she saying, He seem’d to threaten as much; I said, Thank God; then I shall be easy: So she told me all he had said to her, as I have said above.

Mrs. Jervis is very loth I should go; and yet, poor Woman! she begins to be afraid for herself; but would not have me ruin’d for the World. She says, To be sure he means no good; but may be, now he sees me so resolute, he will give over all Attempts: And that I shall know what to do better after To-morrow, when I am to appear before a very bad Judge, I doubt!

O how I dread this To-morrow’s Appearance! But be assured, my dear Parents, of the Honesty of your poor Child! As I am sure I am of your Prayers for

Your dutiful Daughter.

Oh! this frightful To-morrow! how I dread it!

Letter XVI

My dear Parents,

I Know you longed to hear from me soon. I send as soon as I could.

Well, you may believe how uneasily I passed the Time till his appointed Hour came. Every Minute, as it grew nearer, my Terrors increased; and sometimes I had great Courage, and sometimes none at all; and I thought I should faint when it came to the Time my Master had dined. I could neither eat nor drink, for my part; and do what I could, my Eyes were swell’d with crying.

At last he went up to the Closet, which was my good Lady’s Dressing-room; a Room I once lov’d, but then as much hated.

Don’t your Heart ake for me?—I am sure mine flutter’d about like a Bird in a Cage new caught. O Pamela, said I to my self, why art thou so foolish and fearful! Thou hast done no harm! what, if thou fearest an unjust Judge3, when thou art innocent, wouldst thou do before a just one, if thou wert guilty? Have Courage, Pamela, thou knowest the worst! And how easy a Choice Poverty and Honesty is, rather than Plenty and Wickedness?

So I chear’d myself; but yet my poor Heart sunk, and my Spirits were quite broken. Every thing that stirred, I thought was to call me to my Account. I dreaded it, and yet I wished it to come.

Well, at last he rung the Bell; O thought I, that it was my Passing-bell! Mrs. Jervis went up, with a full Heart enough, poor good Woman! He said, Where’s Pamela? let her come up, and do you come with her. She came to me; I was ready to come with my Feet, but my Heart was with my dear Father and Mother, wishing to share your Poverty and Happiness. But I went.

O how can wicked Men look so steddy and untouch’d, with such black Hearts, while poor Innocents look like Malefactors before them!

He looked so stern, that my Heart failed me, and I wish’d myself any-where but there, tho’ I had before been summoning up all my Courage. Good God of Heaven, said I to myself, give me Courage to stand before this naughty Master! O soften him! or harden me!

Come in, Fool, said he, angrily, as soon as he saw me (and snatch’d my Hand with a Pull); you may well be asham’d to see me, after your Noise and Nonsense, and exposing me as you have done. I ashamed to see you! thought I: Very pretty indeed!—But I said nothing.

Mrs. Jervis, said he, here you are both together. Do you sit down; but let her stand if she will: Ay, thought I, if I can; for my Knees beat one against another. Did you not think, when you saw the Girl in the way you found her in, that I had given her the greatest Occasion that could possibly be given any Woman? And that I had actually ruin’d her, as she calls it? Tell me, could you think any thing less? Indeed, says she, I fear’d so at first. Has she told you what I did to her, and all I did to her, to occasion all this Folly, by which my Reputation might have suffer’d in your Opinion, and in that of all the Family?—Tell me, what has she told you?

She was a little too much frighted, as she owned afterwards, at his Sternness, and said, Indeed she told me you only pulled her on your Knee, and kissed her.

Then I plucked up my Spirit a little. Only! Mrs. Jervis, said I, and was not that enough to shew me what I had to fear! When a Master of his Honour’s Degree demeans himself to be so free as that to such a poor Servant as me, what is the next to be expected?—But your Honour went further, so you did; and threaten’d what you would do, and talk’d of Lucretia, and her hard Fate.—Your Honour knows you went too far for a Master to a Servant, or even to his Equal; and I cannot bear it! So I fell a crying most sadly.

Mrs. Jervis began to excuse me, and to beg he would pity a poor Maiden, that had such a Value for her Reputation. He said, I speak it to her Face, I think her very pretty, and I thought her humble, and one that would not grow upon my Favours, or the Notice I took of her; but I abhor the Thought of forcing her to any thing. I know myself better, said he, and what belongs to me: And to be sure I have enough demean’d myself to take so much Notice of such a one as she; but I was bewitch’d, I think, by her, to be freer than became me; tho’ I had no Intention to carry the Jest farther.

What poor Stuff was all this, my dear Mother, from a Man of his Sense! But see how a bad Cause and bad Actions confound the greatest Wits!—It gave me a little more Courage then; for Innocence, I find, in a weak Mind, has many Advantages over Guilt, with all its Riches and Wisdom!

So I said, Your Honour may call this Jest or Sport, or what you please; but indeed, Sir, it is not a Jest that becomes the Distance between a Master and a Servant! Do you hear, Mrs. Jervis, said he? Do you hear the Pertness of the Creature? I had a good deal of this Sort before in the Summer-house, and Yesterday too, which made me rougher to her than perhaps I had otherwise been.

Says Mrs. Jervis, Pamela, don’t be pert to his Honour! You should know your Distance; you see his Honour was only in jest!—O dear Mrs. Jervis, said I, don’t you blame me too! It is very difficult to keep one’s Distance to the greatest of Men, when they won’t keep it themselves to their meanest Servants!

See again, said he; could you believe this of the young Baggage, if you had not heard it. O good your Honour, said the well-meaning Gentlewoman, pity and forgive the poor Girl; she is but a Girl; and her Virtue is very dear to her; and I will pawn my Life for her, she will never be pert to your Honour, if you’ll be so good as to molest her no more, nor frighten her again. Said she, You see how, by her Fit, she was in Terror; she could not help it; and tho’ your Honour intended her no harm; yet the Apprehension was almost Death to her: And I had much ado to bring her to herself again. O the little Hypocrite, said he! she has all the Arts of her Sex; they are born with her; and I told you a-while ago, you did not know her. But, said he, this was not the Reason principally of my calling you before me both together: I find I am likely to suffer in my Reputation by the Perverseness and Folly of this Girl. She has told you all, and perhaps more than all; nay, I make no doubt of it; and she has written Letters; for I find she is a mighty Letter-writer! to her Father and Mother, and others, as far as I know; in which she makes herself an Angel of Light, and me, her kind Master and Benefactor, a Devil incarnate!—(O how People will sometimes, thought I, call themselves by the right Names!—) And all this I won’t bear; and so I am resolv’d she shall return to the Distresses and Poverty she was taken from; and let her take care how she uses my Name with Freedom, when she is gone from me.

I was brighten’d up at once upon these welcome Words: And I threw myself upon my Knees at his Feet, with a most sincere, glad Heart; and I said, God Almighty bless your Honour for your Resolution: Now I shall be happy; and permit me, on my bended Knees, to thank your Honour for all the Benefits and Favours you have heaped upon me: For the Opportunities I have had of Improvement and Learning; through my good Lady’s Means, and yours. I will now forget all your Honour has done to me: And I promise you, that I will never take your Name in my Lips, but with Reverence and Gratitude: And so God Almighty bless your Honour, for ever and ever, Amen!—And so I got up, and went away with another-guise sort of Heart than I came into his Presence with. And so I fell to writing this Letter. And thank God all is over.

And now my dearest Father and Mother, expect to see soon your poor Daughter, with an humble and dutiful Mind, return’d to you: And don’t fear but I know how to be happy with you as ever: For I will lie in the Loft, as I used to do; and pray let the little Bed be got ready; and I have a little Money, which will buy me a Suit of Cloaths, fitter for my Condition than what I have; and I will get Mrs. Mum-ford to help me to some Needle-work; and fear not that I shall be a Burden to you, if my Health continues; and I know God will bless me, if not for my own sake, for both your sakes, who have, in all your Trials and Misfortunes, preserved so much Integrity, as makes every body speak well of you both. But I hope he will let good Mrs. Jervis give me a Character, for fear it should be thought I was turn’d away for Dishonesty.

And so God bless you both, and may you be blest for me, and I blest for you: And I will always bless my Master and Mrs. Jervis. And so good Night; for it is late, and I shall be soon called to-bed.

I hope Mrs. Jervis is not angry with me, because she has not called me to Supper with her; tho’ I could eat nothing if she had. But I make no doubt I shall sleep purely to Night, and dream that I am with you, in my dear, dear, happy Loft once more.

So, good Night again, my dear Father and Mother, says

Your honest poor Daughter.

May-hap I mayn’t come this Week, because I must get up the Linen, and leave every thing belonging to my Place in Order. So send me a Line if you can, to let me know if I shall be welcome, by John, who’ll call for it as he returns. But say nothing of my coming away to him, as yet. For it will be said I blab every thing.

Letter XVII

My dearest Daughter,

Welcome, ten times welcome, shall you be to us; for you come to us innocent, and happy, and honest; and you are the Staff of our Old-age, and our Comfort too4. And tho’ we cannot do for you as we would, yet we doubt not we shall live comfortably together, and what with my diligent Labour, and your poor Mother’s Spinning, and your Needle-work, I make no doubt we shall live better and better. Only your poor Mother’s Eyes begin to fail her; tho’ I bless God, I am as strong, and able, and willing to labour as ever; and Oh my dear Child, your Virtue has made me, I think, stronger and better than I was before. What blessed Things are Trials and Temptations to us, when they be overcome!

But I am thinking about those same four Guineas: I think you should give them back again to your Master; and yet I have broke them. Alas! I have only three left; but I will borrow it if I can, Part upon my Wages, and Part of Mrs. Mumford, and send it to you, that you may return it, against John comes next, if he comes again, before you.

I want to know how you come. I fansy honest John will be glad to bear you Company Part of the Way, if your Master is not so cross as to forbid him. And if I know time enough, your Mother will go one five Miles, and I will go ten on the Way, or till I meet you, as far as one Holiday will go: For that I can get Leave for; and we shall receive you with more Pleasure than we had at your Birth, when all the worst was over; or than we ever had in our Lives.

And so God bless you, till the happy Time comes; say both your Mother and I; which is all at present, from

Your truly loving Parents.

Letter XVIII

Dear Father and Mother

I Thank you a thousand times for your Goodness to me, express’d in your last Letter. I now long to get my Business done, and come to my New-Old Lot, again, as I may call it. I have been quite another thing since my Master has turn’d me off; and as I shall come to you an honest Daughter, what Pleasure it is to what I should have, if I could not have seen you but as a guilty one! Well, my writing Time will soon be over, and so I will make Use of it now, and tell you all that has happen’d since my last Letter.

I wonder’d Mrs. Jervis did not call me to sup with her, and fear’d she was angry; and when I had finish’d my Letter, I long’d for her coming to Bed. At last she came up, but seem’d shy and reserv’d; and I said, O my dear Mrs. Jervis, I am glad to see you: you are not angry with me, I hope. She said she was sorry Things went so far; and that she had a great deal of Talk with my Master after I was gone. She said, he seem’d mov’d at what I said, and at my falling on my Knees to him, and my Prayer for him, at my going away. He said, I was a strange Girl; he knew not what to make of me: And is she gone? said he: I intended to say something else to her, but she behav’d so oddly, that I had not Power to stop her. She ask’d if she should call me again. He said, Yes; and then, No, let her go; it is best for her and me too, that she shall go now I have given her Warning. But where she had it, I can’t tell; but I never met with the Fellow of her in my Life, at any Age. She said, he had order’d her not to tell me all: but she believ’d he never would offer any thing to me again, and I might stay, she fansy’d, if I would beg it as a Favour; tho’ she was not sure neither.

I stay! dear Mrs. Jervis, said I, why ’tis the best News that could have come to me, that he will let me go. I do nothing but long to go back again to my Poverty and Distress, as he said I should; for, tho’ I am sure of the Poverty, I shall not have Half the Distress I have had for some Months past, I’ll assure you.

Mrs. Jervis, dear good Soul, wept over me, and said, Well, well, Pamela, I did not think I had shew’d so little Love to you, as that you should express so much Joy to leave me. I am sure I never had a Child half so dear to me as you!

I cry’d to hear her so good to me, as indeed she has always been; and said, What would you have me to do, dear Mrs. Jervis? I love you next to my own Father and Mother, and you are the chief Concern I have to leave this Place; but I am sure it is certain Ruin if I stay. After such Offers, and such Threatenings, and his comparing himself to a wicked Ravisher, in the very Time of his last Offer; and making a Jest of me, that we should make a pretty Story in Romances; can I stay, and be safe? Has he not demean’d himself twice? and it behoves me to beware of the third Time, for fear he should lay his Snares surer; for may-hap he did not expect a poor Servant would resist her Master so much. And must it not be look’d upon as a sort of Warrant for such Actions, if I stay after this? for I think, when one of our Sex finds she is attempted, it is an Encouragement to a Person to proceed, if one puts one’s self in the Way of it, when one can help it; and it shews one can forgive what in short ought not to be forgiven. Which is no small Countenance to foul Actions, I’ll assure you.

She hugg’d me to her, and said, I’ll assure you! Pretty-face, where gottest thou all thy Knowledge, and thy good Notions, at these Years? Thou art a Miracle for thy Age, and I shall always love thee! But, do you resolve to leave us, Pamela?

Yes, my dear Mrs. Jervis, said I; for as Matters stand, how can I do otherwise?—But I’ll do all the Duties of my Place first, if I may. And I hope you’ll give me a Character as to my Honesty, as it may not look as if I was turn’d away for any Harm. Ay, that I will, said she; I will give thee such a Character as never Girl at thy Years deserv’d. And I am sure, said I, I will always love and honour you, as my third best Friend, where-ever I go, or whatever becomes of me.

And so we went to Bed, and I never wak’d ’till ’twas Time to rise; which I did, as blyth as a Bird, and went about my Business with great Pleasure.

But I believe my Master is fearfully angry with me; for he past by me two or three times, and would not speak to me; and towards Evening he met me in the Passage, going into the Garden, and said such a Word to me as I never heard in my Life from him, to Man, Woman or Child; for he first said, This Creature’s always in my way, I think! I said, standing up as close as I could, and the Entry was wide enough for a Coach too, I hope I shan’t be long in your Honour’s Way. D—n you! said he, (that was the hard Word) for a little Witch; I have no Patience with you.

I profess I trembled to hear him say so; but I saw he was vex’d, and as I am going away, I minded it the less. But I see, my dear Parents, that when a Person will do wicked Things, it is no Wonder he will speak wicked Words. And so I rest

Your dutiful Daughter.

Letter XIX

Dear Father and Mother,

Our John having no Opportunity to go your Way, I write again, and send both Letters at once. I can’t say yet when I can get away, nor how I shall come; because Mrs. Jervis shew’d my Master the Waistcoat I am flowering for him, and he said, It looks well enough, I think the Creature had best stay till she has finish’d it.

There is some private Talk carry’d on betwixt him and Mrs. Jervis, that she don’t tell me of; but yet she is very kind to me, and I don’t mistrust her at all. I should be very base if I did. But to be sure she must oblige him, and keep all his lawful Commands; and other, I dare say, she won’t keep; she is too good, and loves me too well; but she must stay when I am gone, and so must get no Ill-will.

She has been at me again to ask to stay, and humble myself, as she says. But what have I done, Mrs. Jervis, said I? If I have been a Sawce-box, and a Bold-face, and Pert, and a Creature, as he calls me, have I not had Reason? Do you think I should ever have forgot myself, if he had not forgot to act as my Master? Tell me, from your own Heart, dear Mrs. Jervis, said I, if you think I could stay and be safe? What would you think, or how would you act in my Case?

My dear Pamela, said she, and kiss’d me, I don’t know how I should act, or what I should think. I hope I should act as you do. But I know nobody else that would. My Master is a fine Gentleman; he has a great deal of Wit and Sense, and is admir’d, as I know, by half a dozen Ladies, who would think themselves happy in his Addresses. He has a noble Estate; and yet I believe he loves my good Maiden, tho’ his Servant, better than all the Ladies in the Land; and he has try’d to overcome it, because he knows you are so much his Inferior; and ’tis my Opinion he finds he can’t; and that vexes his proud Heart, and makes him resolve you shan’t stay, and so he speaks so cross to you, when he sees you by Accident.

Well, but, Mrs. Jervis, said I, let me ask you, if he can stoop to like such a poor Girl as I, as may be he may, for I have read of Things almost as strange, from great Men to poor Damsels; What can it be for?—He may condescend, may-hap, to think I may be good enough for his Harlot; and those Things don’t disgrace Men, that ruin poor Women, as the World goes. And so, if I was wicked enough, he would keep me till I was undone, and ‘till his Mind changed; for even wicked Men, I have read, soon grow weary of Wickedness of one Sort, and love Variety. Well then, poor Pamela must be turn’d off, and look’d upon as a vile abandon’d Creature, and every body would despise her; ay, and justly too, Mrs. Jervis; for she that can’t keep her Virtue, ought to live in Disgrace.

But, Mrs. Jervis, said I, let me tell you, that I hope, if I was sure he would always be kind to me, and never turn me off at all, that God will give me his Grace, so as to hate and withstand his Temptations, were he not only my Master, but my King, for the Sin’s sake; and this my poor dear Parents have always taught me; and I should be a sad wicked Creature indeed, if, for the sake of Riches or Favour, I should forfeit my good Name: yea, and worse than any other young body of my Sex; because I can so contentedly return to my Poverty again, and think it less Disgrace to be oblig’d to wear Rags, and live upon Rye-bread and Water, as I use to do, than to be a Harlot to the greatest Man in the World.

Good Mrs. Jervis lifted up her Hands, and had her Eyes full of Tears: God bless you, my dear Love, said she; you are my Admiration and Delight!—How shall I do to part with you?

Well, good Mrs. Jervis, said I, let me ask you now:—You and he have had some Talk, and you mayn’t be suffer’d to tell me all. But, do you think, if I was to ask to stay, that he is sorry for what he has done! ay, and asham’d of it too! for I am sure he ought, considering his high Degree, and my low Degree, and how I have nothing in the World to trust to but my Honesty! Do you think in your own Conscience now, pray answer me truly; that he would never offer any thing to me again; and that I could be safe?

Alas! my dear Child, said she, don’t put thy home Questions to me, with that pretty becoming Earnestness in thy Look. I know this, that he is vex’d at what he has done; he was vex’d the first Time, more vex’d the second Time.

Yes, said I, and so he will be vex’d I suppose the third, and the fourth Time too, ‘till he has quite ruin’d your poor Maiden, and who will have Cause to be vex’d then?

Nay, Pamela, said she, don’t imagine that I would be accessary to your Ruin for the World. I only can say, that he has yet done you no Hurt; and ’tis no Wonder that he should love you, you are so pretty; tho’ so much beneath him: But I dare swear for him, he never will offer you any Force.

You say, said I, that he was sorry for his first Offer in the Summer-house; well, and how long did his Sorrow last?—Only ’till he found me by myself; and then he was worse than before: and so became sorry again. And if he has design’d to love me, and you say can’t help it, why he can’t help it neither, if he should have an Opportunity, a third time to distress me. And I have read, that many a Man has been asham’d at a Repulse, that never would, had they succeeded. Besides, Mrs. Jervis, if he really intends to offer no Force, What does that mean?—While you say he can’t help liking me, for Love it cannot be!—Does not it imply, that he hopes to ruin me by my own Consent? I think, said I, (and I hope God would give me Grace to do so) that I should not give way to his Temptations on any Account; but it would be very presumptuous in me to rely upon my own Strength, against a Gentleman of his Qualifications and Estate, and who is my Master; and thinks himself intitled to call me Bold-face, and what not; only for standing on my necessary Defence? And that where the Good of my Soul and Body, and my Duty to God, and my Parents, are all concerned. How then, Mrs. Jervis, said I, can I ask or wish to stay?

Well, well, says she; as he seems very desirous you should not stay, I hope it is from a good Motive; for fear he should be tempted to disgrace himself as well as you. No, no, Mrs. Jervis, said I; I have thought of that too, for I would be glad to think of him with that Duty that becomes me; but then he would have let me gone to Lady Davers, and not have hinder’d my Preferment. And he would not have said, I should return to my Poverty and Distress, when I had been, by his Mother’s Goodness, lifted out of it; but that he intended to fright me, and punish me, as he thought, for not complying with his Wickedness: And this shews me enough what I have to expect from his future Goodness, except I will deserve it at his own dear, dear Price!

She was silent, and I said, Well there’s no more to be said; I must go, that’s certain; All my Concern will be how to part with you: And indeed, next to you, with every body; for all my Fellow-servants have lov’d me, and you and they will cost me a Sigh and a Tear too now-and-then, I am sure; and so I fell a-crying. I could not help it. For it is a pleasant Thing to one to be in a House among a great many Fellow-servants, and be belov’d by them all.

Nay, I should have told you before now, how kind and civil Mr Longman our Steward is: Vastly courteous indeed on all Occasions, and he said, once to Mrs. Jervis, he wish’d he was a young Man for my sake, I should be his Wife, and he would settle all he had upon me on Marriage; and, you must know, he is reckon’d worth a Power of Money.

I take no Pride in this; but bless God, and your good Example, my dear Parents, that I have been enabled to have every body’s good Word. Not but that our Cook one Day, who is a little snappish and cross sometimes, said once to me, Why this Pamela of ours goes as fine as a Lady. See what it is to have a fine Face!—I wonder what the Girl will come to at last!

She was hot with her Work; and I sneak’d away; for I seldom went down in the Kitchen; and I heard the Butler say, Why, Jane, nobody has your good Word! What has Mrs. Pamela done to you? I am sure she offends no body. And what, said the peevish Wench, have I said to her, Foolatum; but that she was pretty? They quarrel’d afterwards, I heard; but I was sorry for it, and troubled myself no more about it. Forgive this silly Prattle, from

Your dutiful Daughter.

O! I forgot to say, that I would stay to finish the Waistcoat; I never did a prettier Piece of Work; and I am up early and late to get it finish’d; for I long to come to you.

1.) Possibly a reference to Hamlet, when upon seeing a ghost Hamelt remarks “Angels and ministers of grace, defend us!” (1.4.43 in Folger Digital Texts).

2.) Lucretia is significant in the mythological founding of the Roman republic. Living when Rome is ruled kings, Lucretia's virtue as a wife and daughter arouse the desire of the king’s youngest son, Sextus Tarquinius. After Sextus rapes Lucretia by sword-point, Lucretia commits suicide, leaving a note which reveals everything. Her death becomes a symbol of monarchal overreach and helps inspire the rebellion that overthrows the king and establishes the Roman republic. Pamela is published in the midst of the Jacobite Risings in which the power of of the British monarch in relationship to Parliament was fiercely contested.

3.) Possibly a reference to the Parable of the Persistent Widow:

1Then Jesus told his disciples a parable to show them that they should always pray and not give up. 2He said: “In a certain town there was a judge who neither feared God nor cared what people thought. 3And there was a widow in that town who kept coming to him with the plea, ‘Grant me justice against my adversary.’

4“For some time he refused. But finally he said to himself, ‘Even though I don’t fear God or care what people think, 5yet because this widow keeps bothering me, I will see that she gets justice, so that she won’t eventually come and attack me!’”

6And the Lord said, “Listen to what the unjust judge says. 7And will not God bring about justice for his chosen ones, who cry out to him day and night? Will he keep putting them off? 8I tell you, he will see that they get justice, and quickly. However, when the Son of Man comes, will he find faith on the earth?” (Luke 18:1-6 NIV)

4.) Possibly a reference to Psalms 23:4:

Even though I walk

through the darkest valley

I will fear no evil

for you are with me;

your rod and your staff

they comfort me. (NIV)

Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday, the 32d, 33d, and 34th Days of my Imprisonment.

Nothing offers these Days but Squabblings between Mrs. Jewkes and me. She grows worse and worse to me. I vexed her yesterday, because she talked nastily, and told her she talk’d more like a vile London Prostitute, than a Gentleman’s Housekeeper; and she cannot use me bad enough for it. Bless me! she curses and storms at me like a Trooper, and can hardly keep her Hands off me. You may believe she must talk sadly to make me say such harsh Words: Indeed it cannot be repeated; and she is a Disgrace to her Sex. And then she ridicules me, and laughs at my Notions of Honesty; and tells me, impudent Creature that she is! what a fine Bedfellow I shall make for my Master, and such-like, with such whimsical Notions about me!—Do you think this is to be borne? And yet she talks worse than this, if possible!—Quite filthily! O what vile Hands am I put into!

Thursday.

I Have now all the Reason that can be, to apprehend my Master will be here soon; for the Servants are all busy in setting the House to rights; and a Stable and Coach-house are cleaning out, that have not been us’d some time. I ask Mrs. Jewkes; but she tells me nothing, nor will hardly answer me when I ask her a Question. Sometimes I think she puts on these strange wicked Airs to me, purposely to make me wish for what I dread most of all Things, my Master’s coming down. He talk of Love!—If he had any the least Notion of Regard for me, to be sure he would not give this naughty Body such Power over me:—And if he does come, where is his Promise of not seeing me without I consent to it? But it seems His Honour owes me nothing! So he tells me in his Letter; and why? Because I am willing to keep mine. But, indeed, he says, he hates me perfectly; and it is plain he does, or I should not be left to the Mercy of this Woman; and, what is worse, to my woful Apprehensions.

Friday, the 36th Day of my Imprisonment.

I Took the Liberty yesterday Afternoon, finding the Gates open, to walk out before the House; and before I was aware, had got to the Bottom of the long Row of Elms; and there I sat myself down upon the Steps of a sort of broad Stile, which leads into the Road, that goes towards the Town. And as I sat musing about what always busies my Mind, I saw a whole Body of Folks, running towards me from the House, Men and Women, as in a Fright. At first I wonder’d what was the Matter, till they came nearer; and I found they were all alarm’d, thinking I had attempted to get off. There was first the horrible Colbrand, running with his long Legs, well nigh two Yards at a Stride; then there was one of the Grooms, poor Mr. Williams’s Robber; then I spy’d Nan, half out of Breath; and the Cook-maid after her; and lastly, came waddling, as fast as she could, Mrs. Jewkes, exclaiming most bitterly, as I found, against me. Colbrand said, O how have you frighted us all!—And went behind me, lest I should run away, as I suppose.

I sat still, to let them see I had no View to get away; for, besides the Improbability of succeeding, my last sad Attempt had cur’d me of enterprizing again. And when Mrs. Jewkes came within hearing, I found her terribly incens’d, and raving about my Contrivances. Why, said I, should you be so concerned? Here I have sat a few Minutes, and had not the least Thought of getting away, or going further; but to return as soon as it was duskish. She would not believe me; and the barbarous Creature struck at me with her horrid Fist, and, I believe, would have felled me, had not Colbrand interposed, and said, He saw me sitting still, looking about me, and not seeming to have the least Inclination to stir. But this would not serve: She order’d the two Maids to take me each by an Arm, and lead me back into the House, and up Stairs; and there have I been locked up ever since, without Shoes. In vain have I pleaded that I had no Design, as, indeed I had not the least; and, last Night I was forced to lie between her and Nan; and I find she is resolved to make a Handle of this against me, and in her own Behalf.—Indeed, what with her Usage, and my own Apprehensions of still worse, I am quite weary of my Life.

Just now she has been with me, and given me my Shoes, and has laid her imperious Commands upon me, to dress myself in a Suit of Cloaths out of the Portmanteau, which I have not seen lately, against three or four o’Clock; for, she says, she is to have a Visit from Lady Darnford’s two Daughters, who come purposely to see me; and so she gave me the Key of the Portmanteau. But I will not obey her; and I told her I would not be made a Shew of, nor see the Ladies. She left me, saying, It should be worse for me, if I did not. But how can that be?

Five o’lock is come,

And no young Ladies!---So that, I fansy---But, hold, I hear their Coach, I believe. I’ll step to the Window.---I won’t go down to them, I am resolv’d.―――――

Good Sirs! good Sirs! What will become of me! Here is my Master come in his fine Chariot!---Indeed he is!—What shall I do? Where shall I hide myself!---Oh! what shall I do!—Pray for me! But Oh! you’ll not see this!—Now, good Heaven preserve me! if it be thy blessed Will!

Seven o’Clock.

Tho’ I dread to see him, yet do I wonder I have not. To be sure something is resolved against me, and he stays to hear all her Stories. I can hardly write; yet, as I can do nothing else, I know not how to forbear!—Yet I cannot hold my Pen!—How crooked and trembling the Lines!—I must leave off, till I can get quieter Fingers!—Why should the Guiltless tremble so, when the Guilty can possess their Minds in Peace!

Saturday Morning.

Now let me give you an Account of what passed last Night; for I had no Power to write, nor yet Opportunity, till now.

This naughty Woman held my Master till half an Hour after seven; and he came hither about five in the Afternoon. And then I heard his Voice on the Stairs, as he was coming up to me. It was about his Supper; for he said, I shall chuse a boil’d Chicken, with Butter and Parsley.—And up he came!

He put on a stern and majestick Air; and he can look very majestick when he pleases. Well, perverse Pamela, ungrateful Runaway, said he, for my first Salutation!—You do well, don’t you, to give me all this Trouble and Vexation? I could not speak; but throwing myself on the Floor, hid my Face, and was ready to die with Grief and Apprehension.—He said, Well may you hide your Face! well may you be ashamed to see me, vile forward one, as you are!—I sobb’d, and wept, but could not speak. And he let me lie, and went to the Door, and called Mrs. Jewkes.—There, said he, take up that fallen Angel!—Once I thought her as innocent as one!—But I have now no Patience with her. The little Hypocrite prostrates herself thus, in hopes to move my Weakness in her Favour, and that I’ll raise her from the Floor myself. But I shall not touch her: No, said he, cruel Gentleman as he was! let such Fellows as Williams be taken in by her artful Wiles; I know her now, and see that she is for any Fool’s Turn, that will be caught by her.

I sighed, as if my Heart would break!—And Mrs. Jewkes lifted me up upon my Knees; for I trembled so, I could not stand. Come, said she, Mrs. Pamela, learn to know your best Friend; confess your unworthy Behaviour, and beg his Honour’s Forgiveness of all your Faults. I was ready to faint; and he said, She is Mistress of Arts, I’ll assure you; and will mimick a Fit, ten to one, in a Minute.

I was struck to the Heart at this; but could not speak presently; only lifted up my Eyes to Heaven!—And at last made shift to say—God forgive you, Sir!—He seem’d in a great Passion, and walked up and down the Room, casting sometimes an Eye to me, and seeming as if he would have spoken, but check’d himself.—And at last he said, When she has acted this her first Part over, perhaps I will see her again, and she shall soon know what she has to trust to.

And so he went out of the Room: And I was quite sick at Heart!—Surely, said I, I am the wickedest Creature that ever breath’d! Well, said the Impertinent, not so wicked as that neither; but I am glad you begin to see your Faults. Nothing like being humble!—Come, I’ll stand your Friend, and plead for you, if you’ll promise to be more dutiful for the future: Come, come, added the Wretch, this may be all made up by to-morrow Morning, if you are not a Fool.—Begone, hideous Woman! said I; and let not my Afflictions be added to by thy inexorable Cruelty, and unwomanly Wickedness!

She gave me a Push, and went away in a violent Passion. And it seems, she made a Story of this; and said, I had such a Spirit, there was no bearing it.

I laid me down on the Floor, and had no Power to stir, till the Clock struck Nine; and then the wicked Woman came up again. You must come down Stairs, said she, to my Master; that is, if you please, Spirit!—Said I, I believe I cannot stand. Then, said she, I’ll send Monsieur Colbrand to carry you down.

I got up, as well as I could, and trembled all the way down Stairs. And she went before me into the Parlour; and a new Servant, that he had waiting on him instead of John, withdrew as soon as I came in.

I thought, said he, when I came down, you should have sat at Table with me, when I had not Company; but when I find you cannot forget your Original, but must prefer my Menials to me, I call you down to wait on me, while I sup, that I may have a little Talk with you, and throw away as little Time as possible upon you.

Sir, said I, you do me Honour to wait upon you—And I never shall, I hope, forget my Original. But I was forced to stand behind his Chair, that I might hold by it. Fill me, said he, a Glass of that Burgundy. I went to do it; but my Hand shook so, that I could not hold the Plate with the Glass in it, and spilt some of the Wine. So Mrs. Jewkes pour’d it for me, and I carry’d it as well as I could; and made a low Curchee. He took it, and said, Stand behind me, out of my Sight!

Why, Mrs. Jewkes, said he, you tell me, she remains very sullen still, and eats nothing. No, said she, not so much as will keep Life and Soul together.—And is always crying, you say, too? said he. Yes, Sir, said she, I think she is, for one thing or another. Ay, said he, your young Wenches will feed upon their Tears; and their Obstinacy will serve them for Meat and Drink. I think I never saw her look better, tho’, in my Life!—But I suppose she lives upon Love. This sweet Mr. Williams, and her little villainous Plots together, have kept her alive and well, to be sure. For Mischief, Love, and Contradiction, are the natural Aliments of a Woman.

Poor I was forced to hear all this, and be silent; and indeed my Heart was too full to speak.

And so you say, said he, that she had another Project, but Yesterday, to get away? She denies it herself, said she; but it had all the Appearance of one. I’m sure she made me in a fearful Pucker about it. And I am glad your Honour is come, with all my Heart; and I hope, whatever be your Honour’s Intention concerning her, you will not be long about it; for you’ll find her as slippery as an Eel, I’ll assure you!

Sir, said I, and clasped his Knees with my Arms, not knowing what I did, and falling on my Knees, Have Mercy on me, and hear me, concerning that wicked Woman’s Usage of me.—

He cruelly interrupted me, and said, I am satisfy’d she has done her Duty: It signifies nothing what you say against Mrs. Jewkes. That you are here, little Hypocrite as you are, pleading your Cause before me, is owing to her Care of you; else you had been with the Parson.—Wicked Girl! said he, to tempt a Man to undo himself, as you have done him, at a Time when I was on the Point of making him happy for his Life!

I arose, but said, with a deep Sigh, I have done, Sir, I have done! I have a strange Tribunal to plead before. The poor Sheep, in the Fable, had such an one; when it was try’d before the Vultur, on the Accusation of the Wolf19

So, Mrs. Jewkes, said he, you are the Wolf, I the Vultur, and this the poor innocent Lamb, on her Trial before us.—Oh! you don’t know how well this Innocent is read in Reflection. She has Wit at Will, when she has a mind to display her own romantick Innocence, at the Price of other People’s Characters.

Well, said the aggravating Creature, this is nothing to what she has called me; I have been a Jezebel, a London Prostitute, and what not?—But I am contented with her ill Names, now I see it is her Fashion, and she can call your Honour a Vultur.

Said I, I had no Thought of comparing my Master—And was going to say on: But he said, Don’t prate, Girl!—No, said she, it don’t become you, I’ll assure you.

Well, said I, since I must not speak, I will hold my Peace: But there is a righteous Judge, who knows the Secrets of all Hearts!20 and to him I appeal.

See there! said he: Now this meek, good Creature is praying for Fire from Heaven upon us! O she can curse most heartily, in the Spirit of Christian Meekness, I’ll assure you!—Come, Sawcy-face, give me another Glass of Wine!

So I did, as well as I could; but wept so, that he said, I suppose I shall have some of your Tears in my Wine!

When he had supp’d, he stood up, and said, O how happy for you it is, that you can, at Will, thus make your speaking Eyes overflow in this manner, without losing any of their Brilliancy! you have been told, I suppose, that you are most beautiful in your Tears!—Did you ever, said he to her, (who all this while was standing in one Corner of the Parlour) see a more charming Creature than this? Is it to be wonder’d at, that I demean myself thus to take Notice of her!—See, said he, and took the Glass with one Hand, and turn’d me round with the other, What a Shape! what a Neck! what a Hand! and what a Bloom in that lovely Face!—But who can describe the Tricks and Artifices, that lie lurking in her little, plotting, guileful Heart! ’Tis no Wonder the poor Parson was infatuated with her!—I blame him less than her; for who could expect such Artifice in so young a Sorceress!

I went to the further Part of the Room, and held my Face against the Wainscot; and, in spite of all I could do to refrain crying, sobb’d, as if my Heart would break. He said, I am surpriz’d, Mrs. Jewkes, at the Mistake of the Letters you tell me of! But, you see, I am not afraid any body should read what I write. I don’t carry on private Correspondencies, and reveal every Secret that comes to my Knowledge, and then corrupt People to carry my Letters, against their Duty, and all good Conscience.

Come hither, Hussy, said he; you and I have a dreadful Reckoning to make.—Why don’t you come, when I bid you?—Fie upon it! Mrs. Pamela, said she, what! not stir, when his Honour commands you to come to him!—Who knows but his Goodness will forgive you?

He came to me, (for I had no Power to stir) and put his Arms about my Neck, and would kiss me; and said, Well, Mrs. Jewkes, if it were not for the Thought of this cursed Parson, I believe in my Heart, so great is my Weakness, that I could yet forgive this intriguing little Slut, and take her to my Bosom.

O, said the Sycophant, you are very good, Sir, very forgiving, indeed!—But come, added the profligate Wretch, I hope you will be so good, as to take her to your Bosom; and that, by to-morrow Morning, you’ll bring her to a better Sense of her Duty!

Could any thing, in Womanhood, be so vile! I had no Patience: But yet Grief and Indignation choaked up the Passage of my Words; and I could only stammer out a passionate Exclamation to Heaven, to protect my Innocence. But the Word was the Subject of their Ridicule. Was ever poor Creature worse beset!

He said, as if he had been considering whether he could forgive me or not, No, I cannot yet forgive her neither—She has given me great Disturbance; has brought great Discredit upon me, both abroad and at home; has corrupted all my Servants at the other House; has despised my honourable Views and Intentions to her, and sought to run away with this ingrateful Parson—And surely I ought not to forgive her all this!—Yet, with all this wretched Grimace, he kissed me again, and would have put his Hand in my Bosom; but I struggled, and said, I would die before I would be used thus.—Consider, Pamela, said he, in a threatening Tone, consider where you are! and don’t play the Fool: If you do, a more dreadful Fate awaits you than you expect. But, take her up Stairs, Mrs. Jewkes, and I’ll send a few Lines to her to consider of; and let me have your Answer, Pamela, in the Morning. Till then you have to resolve upon: And after that, your Doom is fix’d.—So I went up Stairs, and gave myself up to Grief and Expectation of what he would send: But yet I was glad of this Night’s Reprieve!

He sent me, however, nothing at all. And about Twelve o’Clock, Mrs. Jewkes and Nan came up, as the Night before, to be my Bedfellows; and I would go to-bed with two of my Petticoats on; which they mutter’d at sadly; and Mrs. Jewkes railed at me particularly: Indeed I would have sat up all Night, for Fear, if she would have let me. For I had but very little Rest that Night, apprehending this Woman would let my Master in. She did nothing but praise him, and blame me; but I answer’d her as little as I could.

He has Sir Simon Tell-tale, alias Darnford, to dine with him to-day, whose Family sent to welcome him into the Country; and it seems, the old Knight wants to see me; so I suppose I shall be sent for, as Samson21 was, to make Sport for him—Here I am, and must bear it all!

Twelve o’Clock Saturday Noon.

Just now he has sent me up, by Mrs. Jewkes, the following Proposals. So here are the honourable Intentions all at once laid open. They are, my dear Parents, to make me a vile kept Mistress: Which God, I hope, will always enable me to detest the Thoughts of. But you’ll see how they are accommodated to what I should have most lov’d, could I have honestly promoted it, your Welfare and Happiness. I have answer’d them, as you’ll, I’m sure, approve; and I am prepared for the worst: For tho’ I fear there will be nothing omitted to ruin me, and tho’ my poor Strength will not be able to defend me, yet I will be innocent of Crime in my Intention, and in the Sight of God; and to him leave the avenging of all my Wrongs, in his own good Time and Manner. I shall write to you my Answer against his Articles; and hope the best, tho’ I fear the worst. But if I should come home to you ruin’d and undone, and may not be able to look you in the Face; yet pity and inspirit the poor Pamela, to make her little Remnant of Life easy; for long I shall not survive my Disgrace. And you may be assured it shall not be my Fault, if it be my Misfortune.

To Mrs. Pamela Andrews.

The following Articles are proposed to your serious Consideration; and let me have an Answer, in Writing, to them; that I may take my Resolutions accordingly. Only remember, that I will not be trifled with; and what you give for Answer, will absolutely decide your Fate, without Expostulation or further Trouble.

This is my Answer.

Forgive, good Sir, the Spirit your poor Servant is about to shew in her Answer to your Articles. Not to be warm, and in earnest, on such an Occasion as the present, would shew a Degree of Guilt, that, I hope, my Soul abhors. I will not trifle with you, nor act like a Person doubtful of her own Mind; for it wants not one Moment’s Consideration with me; and I therefore return the Answer following, let what will be the Consequence.

I. If you can convince me, that the hated Parson has had no Encouragement from you in his Addresses; and that you have no Inclination for him, in Preference to me; then I will offer the following Proposals to you, which I will punctually make good.

I. As to the first Article, Sir, it may behove me, that I may not deserve, in your Opinion, the opprobrious Terms of forward and artful, and the like, to declare solemnly, that Mr. Williams never had the least Encouragement from me, as to what you hint; and I believe his principal Motive was the apprehended Duty of his Function, quite contrary to his apparent Interest, to assist a Person he thought in Distress. You may, Sir, the rather believe me, when I declare, that I know not the Man breathing I would wish to marry; and that the only one I could honour more than another, is the Gentleman, who, of all others, seeks my everlasting Dishonour.

II. I will directly make you a Present of 500 Guineas, for your own Use, which you may dispose of to any Purpose you please: And will give it absolutely into the Hands of any Person you shall appoint to receive it; and expect no Favour in Return, till you are satisfy’d in the Possession of it.

II. As to your second Proposal, let the Consequence be what it will, I reject it with all my Soul. Money, Sir, is not my chief Good: May God Almighty desert me, whenever it is; and whenever, for the sake of that, I can give up my Title to that blessed Hope which will stand me in stead, at a Time when Millions of Gold will not purchase one happy Moment of Reflection on a past mis-spent Life!

III. I will likewise directly make over to you a Purchase I lately made in Kent, which brings in 250 l. per Annum, clear of all Deductions. This shall be made over to you in full Property for your Life, and for the Lives of any Children, to Perpetuity, that you may happen to have: And your Father shall be immediately put into Possession of it, in Trust for these Purposes. And the Management of it will yield a comfortable Subsistence to him and your Mother, for Life; and I will make up any Deficiencies, if such should happen, to that clear Sum, and allow him 50 l. per Annum besides, for his Life, and that of your Mother, for his Care and Management of this your Estate.

III. Your third Proposal, Sir, I reject, for the same Reason; and am sorry you could think my poor honest Parents would enter into their Part of it, and be concerned for the Management of an Estate, which would be owing to the Prostitution of their poor Daughter. Forgive, Sir, my Warmth on this Occasion; but you know not the poor Man, and the poor Woman, my ever dear Father and Mother, if you think that they would not much rather chuse to starve in a Ditch, or rot in a noisome Dunghil, than accept of the Fortune of a Monarch, upon such wicked Terms. I dare not say all that my full Mind suggests to me on this grievous Occasion.—But indeed, Sir, you know them not; nor shall the Terrors of Death, in its most frightful Forms, I hope, thro’ God’s assisting Grace, ever make me act unworthy of such poor honest Parents.

IV. I will, moreover, extend my Favour to any other of your Relations, that you may think worthy of it, or that are valued by you.

IV. Your fourth Proposal, I take upon me, Sir, to answer as the third. If I have any Friends that want the Favour of the Great, may they ever want it, if they are capable of desiring it on unworthy Terms!

V. I will, besides, order Patterns to be sent you for chusing four complete Suits of rich Cloaths, that you may appear with Reputation, as if you was my Wife. And I will give you the two Diamond Rings, and two Pair of Ear-rings, and Diamond Necklace, that were bought by my Mother, to present to Miss Tomlins, if the Match had been brought to Effect, that was proposed between her and me: And I will confer upon you still other Gratuities, as I shall find myself obliged, by your good Behaviour and Affection.

V. Fine Cloaths, Sir, become not me; nor have I any Ambition to wear them. I have greater Pride in my Poverty and Meanness, than I should have in Dress and Finery. Believe me, Sir, I think such things less become the humble-born Pamela, than the Rags your good Mother raised me from. Your Rings, Sir, your Necklace, and your Ear-rings, will better befit Ladies of Degree, than me: And to lose the best Jewel, my Virtue, would be poorly recompensed by those you propose to give me. What should I think, when I looked upon my Finger, or saw, in the Glass, those Diamonds on my Neck, and in my Ears, but that they were the Price of my Honesty; and that I wore those Jewels outwardly, because I had none inwardly?

VI. Now, Pamela, will you see by this, what a Value I set upon the Free-will of a Person already in my Power; and who, if these Proposals are not accepted, shall find that I have not taken all these Pains, and risqued my Reputation, as I have done, without resolving to gratify my Passion for you, at all Adventures, and if you refuse, without making any Terms at all.

VI. I know, Sir, by woful Experience, that I am in your Power: I know all the Resistance I can make will be poor and weak, and perhaps stand me in little stead: I dread your Will to ruin me is as great as your Power: Yet, Sir, will I dare to tell you, that I will make no Free will Offering of my Virtue. All that I can do, poor as it is, I will do, to convince you, that your Offers shall have no Part in my Choice; and if I cannot escape the Violence of Man, I hope, by God’s Grace, I shall have nothing to reproach myself, for not doing all in my Power to avoid my Disgrace; and then I can safely appeal to the great God, my only Refuge and Protector, with this Consolation, That my Will bore no Part in my Violation.

VII. You shall be Mistress of my Person and Fortune, as much as if the foolish Ceremony had passed. All my Servants shall be yours; and you shall chuse any two Persons to attend yourself, either Male or Female, without any Controul of mine; and if your Conduct be such, that I have Reason to be satisfied with it, I know not (but will not engage for this) that I may, after a Twelve-month’s Cohabitation, marry you; for if my Love increases for you, as it has done for many Months past, it will be impossible for me to deny you any thing.

And now, Pamela, consider well, it is in your Power to oblige me on such Terms, as will make yourself, and all your Friends, happy: But this will be over this very Day, irrevocably over; and you shall find all you would be thought to fear, without the least Benefit arising from it to yourself.—And I beg you’ll well weigh the Matter, and comply with my Proposals; and I will instantly set about securing to you the full Effect of them: And let me, if you value yourself, experience a grateful Return on this Occasion; and I’ll forgive all that’s past.

VII. I have not once dared to look so high, as to such a Proposal as your seventh Article contains. Hence have proceeded all my little, abortive Artifices to escape from the Confinement you have put me in; altho’ you promised to be honourable to me. Your Honour, well I knew, would not let you stoop to so mean and so unworthy a Slave, as the poor Pamela: All I desire is, to be permitted to return to my native Meanness unviolated. What have I done, Sir, to deserve it should be otherwise? For the obtaining of this, tho’ I would not have marry’d your Chaplain, yet would I have run away with your meanest Servant, if I had thought I could have got safe to my beloved Poverty. I heard you once say, Sir, That a certain great Commander, who could live upon Lentils22, might well refuse the Bribes of the greatest Monarch; and, I hope, as I can contentedly live at the meanest Rate, and think not myself above the lowest Condition, that I am also above making an Exchange of my Honesty for all the Riches of the Indies. When I come to be proud and vain of gaudy Apparel, and outside Finery; then, (which, I hope, will never be) may I rest my principal Good in such vain Trinkets, and despise for them the more solid Ornaments of a good Fame, and a Chastity inviolate!

Give me Leave to say, Sir, in Answer to what you hint, That you may, in a Twelvemonth’s Time, marry me, on the Continuance of my good Behaviour; that this weighs less with me, if possible, than any thing else you have said. For, in the first Place, there is an End of all Merit, and all good Behaviour, on my Side, if I have now any, the Moment I consent to your Proposals. And I should be so far from expecting such an Honour, that I will pronounce, that I should be most unworthy of it. What, Sir, would the World say, were you to marry your Harlot?—That a Gentleman of your Rank in Life, should stoop, not only to the base-born Pamela, but to a base-born Prostitute?—Little, Sir, as I know of the World, I am not to be caught by a Bait so poorly cover’d as this!

Yet, after all, dreadful is the Thought, that I, a poor, weak, friendless, unhappy Creature, am too fully in your Power! But permit me, Sir, to pray, as I now write, on my bended Knees, That before you resolve upon my Ruin, you will weigh well the Matter. Hitherto, Sir, tho’ you have taken large Strides to this crying Sin, yet are you on this Side the Commission of it—When once it is done, nothing can recal it! And where will be your Triumph?—What Glory will the Spoils of such a weak Enemy yield you? Let me but enjoy my Poverty with Honesty, is all my Prayer; and I will bless you, and pray for you every Moment of my Life! Think, O think! before it is yet too late! what Stings, what Remorse will attend your dying Hour, when you come to reflect, that you have ruin’d, perhaps Soul and Body, a wretched Creature, whose only Pride was her Virtue! And how pleas’d you will be, on the contrary, if in that tremendous Moment you shall be able to acquit yourself of this foul Crime, and to plead in your own Behalf, that you suffer’d the earnest Supplications of an unhappy Wretch to prevail with you to be innocent yourself, and let her remain so!—May God Almighty, whose Mercy so lately sav’d you from the Peril of perishing in deep Waters, (on which, I hope, you will give me Cause to congratulate you!) touch your Heart in my Favour, and save you from this Sin, and me from this Ruin!—And to Him do I commit my Cause; and to Him will I give the Glory, and Night and Day pray for you, if I may be permitted to escape this great Evil!—From

Your poor, oppressed
broken-spirited, Servant.

I took a Copy of this for your Perusal, if I shall ever be so happy to see you again, my dear Parents (for I hope my Conduct shall be approved of by you); and at Night, when Sir Simon was gone, he sent for me down. Well, said he, have you considered my Proposals? Yes, Sir, said I, I have: And there is my Answer. But pray let me not see you read it. Is it your Bashfulness, said he, or your Obstinacy, that makes you not chuse I should read it before you?

I offer’d to go away; and he said, Don’t run from me; I won’t read it till you are gone. But, said he, tell me, Pamela, whether you comply with my Proposals, or not? Sir, said I, you will see presently; pray don’t hold me; for he took my Hand. Said he, Did you well consider before you answer’d?—I did, Sir, said I. If it be not what you think will please me, said he, dear Girl, take it back again, and reconsider it; for if I have this as your absolute Answer, and I don’t like it, you are undone; for I will not sue meanly, where I can command. I fear, said he, it is not what I like, by your Manner. And, let me tell you, That I cannot bear Denial. If the Terms I have offer’d are not sufficient, I will augment them to two Thirds of my Estate; for, said he, and swore a dreadful Oath, I cannot live without you: And since the thing is gone so far, I will not!—And so he clasped me in his Arms, in such a manner as quite frighted me; and kissed me two or three times.

I got from him, and run up Stairs, and went to the Closet, and was quite uneasy and fearful.

In an Hour’s time, he called Mrs. Jewkes down to him; and I heard him very high in Passion: And all about poor me! And I heard her say, It was his own Fault; there would be an End of all my Complaining and Perverseness, if he was once resolved; and other most impudent Aggravations. I am resolved not to go to-bed this Night, if I can help it—Lie still, lie still, my poor fluttering Heart!—what will become of me!

Almost Twelve o’Clock Saturday Night.

He sent Mrs. Jewkes, about Ten o’Clock, to tell me to come to him. Where? said I. I’ll shew you, said she. I went down three or four Steps, and saw her making to his Chamber, the Door of which was open: So I said, I cannot go there!—Don’t be foolish, said she; but come; no Harm will be done to you!—Well, said I, if I die, I cannot go there. I heard him say, Let her come, or it shall be worse for her. I can’t bear, said he, to speak to her myself!—Well, said I, I cannot come, indeed I cannot; and so I went up again into my Closet, expecting to be fetch’d by Force.

But she came up soon after, and bid me make haste to-bed: Said I, I will not go to-bed this Night, that’s certain!—Then, said she, you shall be made to come to-bed; and Nan and I will undress you. I knew neither Prayers nor Tears would move this wicked Woman: So, I said, I am sure you will let my Master in, and I shall be undone! Mighty Piece of Undone, she said! But he was too exasperated against me, to be so familiar with me, she would assure me—Ay, said she, you’ll be disposed of another way soon, I can tell you for your Comfort; And I hope your Husband will have your Obedience, tho’ nobody else can. No Husband in the World, said I, shall make me do an unjust or base thing.—She said, That would be soon try’d; and Nan coming in, What, said I, am I to have two Bedfellows again, these warm Nights? Yes, said she, Slippery-ones, you are, till you can have one good one instead of us. Said I, Mrs. Jewkes, don’t talk nastily to me. I see you are beginning again; and I shall affront you, may-be; for next to bad Actions, are bad Words, for they could not be spoken, if they were not in the Heart.—Come to-bed, Purity! said she. You are a Nonsuch, I suppose. Indeed, said I, I can’t come to-bed; and it will do you no harm to let me sit all Night in the great Chair. Nan, said she, undress my young Lady. If she won’t let you, I’ll help you: And if neither of us can do it quietly, we’ll call my Master to do it for us; tho’, said she, I think it an Office worthier of Monsieur Colbrand!—You are very wicked, said I. I know it, said she: I am a Jezebel, and a London Prostitute, you know. You did great Feats, said I, to tell my Master all this poor Stuff! But you did not tell him how you beat me: No, Lambkin, said she, (a Word I had not heard a good while) that I left for you to tell; and you was going to do it, if the Vultur had not taken the Wolf’s Part, and bid the poor innocent Lamb be silent!—Ay, said I, no matter for your Fleers, Mrs. Jewkes; tho’ I can have neither Justice nor Mercy here, and cannot be heard in my Defence, yet a Time will come, may-be, when I shall be heard, and when your own Guilt will strike you dumb—Ay, Spirit! said she; and the Vultur too! Must we both be dumb? Why that, Lambkin, will be pretty!—Then, said the wicked one, you’ll have all the Talk to yourself!—Then how will the Tongue of the pretty Lambkin bleat out Innocence, and Virtue, and Honesty, till the whole Trial be at an End!—You’re a wicked Woman, that’s certain, said I; and if you thought any thing of another World, could not talk thus. But no Wonder!—It shews what Hands I am got into!—Ay, so it does, said she; but I beg you’ll undress, and come to-bed, or I believe your Innocence won’t keep you from still worse Hands. I will come to bed, said I, if you will let me have the Keys in my own Hand; not else, if I can help it. Yes, said she, end then, hey! for another Contrivance, another Escape!—No, no, said I, all my Contrivances are over, I’ll assure you! Pray let me have the Keys, and I will come to-bed. She came to me, and took me in her huge Arms, as if I was a Feather; said she, I do this to shew you, what a poor Resistance you can make against me, if I pleased to exert myself; and so, Lambkin, don’t say to your Wolf, I won’t come to-bed!—And set me down, and tapped me on the Neck: Ah! said she, thou art a pretty Creature, it’s true; but so obstinate! so full of Spirit! If thy Strength was but answerable to that, thou wouldst run away with us all, and this great House too on thy Back! but undress, undress, I tell you.

Well, said I, I see my Misfortunes make you very merry, and very witty too: But I will love you, if you will humour me with the Keys of the Chamber-doors.—Are you sure you will love me, said she?—Now speak your Conscience!—Why, said I, you must not put it so close; neither would you, if you thought you had not given Reason to doubt it!—But I will love you as well as I can!—I would not tell a wilful Lye: And if I did, you would not believe me, after your hard Usage of me. Well, said she, that’s all fair, I own!—But Nan, pray pull off my young Lady’s Shoes and Stockens.—No, pray don’t, said I; I will come to-bed presently, since I must.

And so I went to the Closet, and scribbled a little about this idle Chit-chat. And she being importunate, I was forced to go to-bed; but with two of my Coats on, as the former Night; and she let me hold the two Keys; for there are two Locks, there being a double Door; and so I got a little Sleep that Night, having had none for two or three Nights before.

I can’t imagine what she means; but Nan offer’d to talk a little once or twice; and she snubbed her, and said, I charge you, Wench, don’t open your Lips before me! And if you are asked any Questions by Mrs. Pamela, don’t answer her one Word, while I am here!—But she is a lordly Woman to the Maid-servants, and that has always been her Character. O how unlike good Mrs. Jervis in every thing!

19.) Refers to another fable in Richardson’s Æsop's Fables, "The sheep and Wolf". See the Appendix.

20.) Refers to the first words spoken to a bride and groom during the wedding service in the Common Prayer Book of the Church of England (1662):

I require and charge you both, (as ye will answer at the dreadful day of judgment when the secrets of all hearts shall be disclosed) that if either of you know any impediment, why ye may not be lawfully joined together in Matrimony, ye do now confess it. For be ye well assured, that so many as are coupled together otherwise than God’s Word doth allow, are not joined together by God, neither is their Matrimony lawful.

21.) Samson is an old-testament hero who, once defeated, was humiliated by his captors by being forced to entertain them. In spite of being wounded, Samson is able to bring the roof down, killing everyone (Judges 16).

22.) Manius Curius Dentatus was a Roman general celebrated in Plutarch’s Lives as being so humble as to return gifts given for winning a battle, saying all he needed was his simple supper.